<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech or declaration of John Pym, Esquire after the recapitulation or summing up of the charge of high-treason, against Thomas, Earl of Strafford, 12 April, 1641.</title>
            <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4293</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16945</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11734023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11734023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 545:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech or declaration of John Pym, Esquire after the recapitulation or summing up of the charge of high-treason, against Thomas, Earl of Strafford, 12 April, 1641.</title>
                  <author>Pym, John, 1584-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 29 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bartlet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Strafford, Thomas Wentworth, --  Earl of, 1593-1641.</term>
               <term>Treason.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:48451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> THE SPEECH OR DECLARATION OF <hi>JOHN PYM,</hi>
Eſquire: After the Recapitulation or ſumming up of the Charge of
<hi>High-Treaſon, AGAINST</hi> THOMAS, EARLE OF STRAFFORD, 12. APRIL,
1641.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the</hi> COMMONS HOUSE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for JOHN BARTLET, 1641.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48451:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48451:2"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OR DECLARATION OF <hi>JOHN PYM,</hi>
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any dayes have been ſpent in maintenance of the Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of the <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Strafford,</hi> by the <hi>Houſe</hi> of
<hi>Commons,</hi> whereby he ſtands charged with <hi>High Treaſon:</hi> And
your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> have heard his <hi>Defence</hi> with
<hi>Patience,</hi> and with as much favour as <hi>Iuſtice</hi> would allow:
We have paſſed through our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48451:3"/> 
               <hi>Evidence,</hi> and the <hi>Reſult</hi> of
all this is, that it remaines clearly proved, <hi>That the Earle of Strafford
hath indeavoured by his words, actions, and counſels, to ſubvert the
Fundamentall Lawes of England and Ireland, and to introduce an Arbitrary and
Tyrannicall Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>envenomed Arrow</hi> for which he inquired in the
beginning of his <hi>Replication</hi> this day, which hath infected all his
<hi>Bloud:</hi> This is that <hi>Intoxicating Cup,</hi> (to uſe his owne
Metaphor) which hath tainted his <hi>Iudgement,</hi> and poiſoned his
<hi>Heart:</hi> From hence was infuſed that <hi>Specificall Difference</hi>
which tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his <hi>Speeches,</hi> his <hi>Actions,</hi> his
<hi>Counſels</hi> into <hi>Treaſon;</hi> Not <hi>Cumulative,</hi> as he
expreſt it, as if many <hi>Miſdemeanours</hi> could make one
<hi>Treaſon;</hi> but <hi>Formally</hi> and <hi>Eſſentially.</hi> It is
the <hi>End</hi> that doth informe <hi>Actions,</hi> and doth
<hi>ſpecificate</hi> the <hi>nature</hi> of them, making not onely
<hi>criminall,</hi> but even <hi>indifferent words</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> to
be <hi>Treaſon,</hi> being done and ſpoken with a <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
intention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which is given me in <hi>charge,</hi> is, to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48451:3"/> ſhew the <hi>quality</hi> of the
<hi>offence,</hi> how <hi>hainous</hi> it is in the <hi>nature,</hi> how
<hi>miſchievous</hi> in the <hi>effect</hi> of it; which will beſt appeare
if it be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by that <hi>Law,</hi> to which he himſelfe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, that
<hi>univerſall,</hi> that <hi>ſupreme Law, Salus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli:</hi> This is the
<hi>Element</hi> of all Laws, out of which they are derived; the <hi>End</hi>
of all Laws, to which they are deſigned, and in which they are perfected. How
far it ſtands in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to this <hi>Law,</hi> I ſhall endeavour to
ſhew in ſome <hi>Conſiderations</hi> which I ſhal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your
Lordſhips, all ariſing out of the <hi>Evidence</hi> which hath been
opened.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this: It is an offence <hi>comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> all other offences; here you ſhall finde ſeverall
<hi>Treaſons, Murders, Rapines, Oppreſsions, Perjuries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Earth</hi> hath a <hi>Seminarie vertue,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it
doth produce all <hi>Hearbs,</hi> and <hi>Plants,</hi> and other
<hi>Vegetables:</hi> There is in this <hi>Crime,</hi> a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minarie</hi> of
all <hi>evils</hi> hurtfull to a <hi>State;</hi> and if you conſider the
<hi>reaſons</hi> of it, it muſt needs be ſo: The <hi>Law</hi> is that
which puts a <hi>difference</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48451:4"/> betwixt <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill,</hi>
betwixt <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>unjuſt;</hi> If you take away the
<hi>Law,</hi> all things will fall into a <hi>confuſion, every man</hi> will
become a <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> which in the <hi>depraved
condition</hi> of <hi>humane nature,</hi> muſt needs <hi>produce</hi> many
great <hi>enormities: Luſt</hi> will become a <hi>Law,</hi> and
<hi>Envie</hi> will become a <hi>Law, Covetouſneſſe</hi> and
<hi>Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> will become <hi>Lawes;</hi> and what <hi>dictates,</hi> what
<hi>deciſions</hi> ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> will produce, may eaſily be
diſcerned in the late <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Ireland:</hi> The
<hi>Law</hi> hath a <hi>power</hi> to <hi>prevent,</hi> to
<hi>reſtraine,</hi> to <hi>repaire evils;</hi> without this all kind of
<hi>miſchiefs</hi> and <hi>diſtempers</hi> will <hi>break in upon a
State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the <hi>Law</hi> that doth <hi>intitle</hi> the
<hi>King</hi> to the <hi>Allegeance</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> of his
<hi>people;</hi> it <hi>intitles</hi> the <hi>people</hi> to the
<hi>protection</hi> and <hi>juſtice</hi> of the <hi>King. It is God alone who
ſubſiſts by himſelfe,</hi> all other things <hi>ſubſiſt</hi> in a
<hi>mutuall dependence</hi> and <hi>relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> He was a wiſe man that
ſaid, that the King <hi>ſubſiſted</hi> by the field that is
<hi>tilled:</hi> It is the <hi>labour</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> that
ſupports the <hi>Crowne:</hi> If you take away the <hi>protection</hi> of the
<hi>King,</hi> the <hi>vigour</hi> and <hi>cheerfulneſs</hi> of
<hi>Allegeance</hi> will be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, though the <hi>Obligation</hi>
remaine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48451:4"/> The <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>Boundarie,</hi> the
<hi>Meaſure</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Kings Prerogative,</hi> and the <hi>Peoples
Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty:</hi> Whiles theſe move in their owne <hi>Orbe,</hi> they are a
<hi>ſupport</hi> and <hi>ſecurity</hi> to one another; The
<hi>Prerogative</hi> a <hi>cover</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> to the
<hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> and the <hi>people</hi> by their
<hi>liberty</hi> are enabled to be a <hi>foundation</hi> to the
<hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive;</hi> but if theſe <hi>bounds</hi> be ſo removed, that
they enter into <hi>conteſtation</hi> and <hi>conflict,</hi> one of theſe
<hi>miſchiefes</hi> muſt needs enſue: If the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> of the
<hi>King overwhelm</hi> the <hi>liberty</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> it will be
turned into <hi>Tyrannie;</hi> if <hi>liberty undermine</hi> the
<hi>Prerogative,</hi> it will grow into <hi>Anarchie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>ſafeguard,</hi> the
<hi>cuſtody</hi> of all <hi>private intereſt:</hi> Your <hi>Honours,</hi>
your <hi>Lives,</hi> your <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> are all in
the <hi>keeping</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> without this, every man hath a like
<hi>right</hi> to any thing, and this is the <hi>condition</hi> into which the
<hi>Iriſh</hi> were brought by the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Strafford:</hi> And the
<hi>reaſon</hi> which he gave for it, hath more <hi>miſchiefe</hi> in it
then the thing it ſelfe, <hi>They were a Conquered Nation.</hi> There can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be a word more <hi>pregnant,</hi> and <hi>fruitfull</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48451:5"/> in <hi>Treaſon,</hi> then that word is: There
are few <hi>Nations</hi> in the world that have not been <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered;</hi>
and no doubt but the <hi>Conquerour</hi> may give what <hi>Lawes</hi> he
pleaſe to thoſe that are <hi>conquered:</hi> But if the <hi>ſucceeding
Pacts</hi> and <hi>Agreements</hi> doe not limit and reſtraine that
<hi>Right,</hi> what people can be ſecure? <hi>England</hi> hath been
<hi>conquered,</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi> hath been <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered,</hi> and by
this reaſon will be in little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>caſe</hi> then <hi>Ireland.</hi>
If the <hi>King</hi> by the <hi>Right</hi> of a <hi>Conquerour</hi> gives
<hi>Lawes</hi> to his <hi>People,</hi> ſhall not the people by the ſame
<hi>reaſon</hi> be reſtored to the <hi>Right</hi> of the
<hi>conquered,</hi> to recover their <hi>liberty</hi> if they can? What can be
more <hi>hurtfull,</hi> more <hi>pernicious</hi> to both, then ſuch
<hi>Propoſitions</hi> as theſe? And in theſe particulars is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
the <hi>firſt Conſideration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond Conſideration</hi> is this: This
<hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>power</hi> is <hi>dangerous</hi> to
the <hi>Kings Perſon,</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> to his <hi>Crown:</hi> It
is apt to cheriſh <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, uſurpation,</hi> and <hi>oppreſsion</hi>
in great men, and to beget <hi>ſedition</hi> and <hi>diſcontent</hi> in the
<hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> and both theſe have beene, and in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt ever be
<hi>cauſes</hi> of great <hi>trouble</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48451:5"/> 
               <hi>alteration</hi> to <hi>Princes</hi> and
<hi>States.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of thoſe <hi>Eaſterne
Countries</hi> be peruſed, where <hi>Princes</hi> order their
<hi>affaires</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>miſchievous principles</hi> of the
<hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Strafford, looſe and abſolved from all Rules of
Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> they will be found to be <hi>frequent</hi> in
<hi>combuſtions,</hi> full of <hi>Maſſacres,</hi> and of the
<hi>tragicall ends</hi> of <hi>Princes.</hi> If any man ſhall look into our
owne <hi>Stories,</hi> in the times when the <hi>Laws</hi> were moſt
neglected, he ſhall find them full of <hi>Commotions,</hi> of <hi>Civill
diſtempers;</hi> whereby the <hi>Kings</hi> that then reigned, were alwayes
kept in <hi>want</hi> and <hi>diſtreſſe;</hi> the people conſumed with
<hi>Civill wars:</hi> and by ſuch wicked <hi>counſels</hi> as theſe,
ſome of our <hi>Princes</hi> have beene brought to ſuch miſerable
<hi>ends,</hi> as no <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi> heart can remember without
<hi>horrour,</hi> and <hi>earneſt Prayer,</hi> that it may never be ſo
againe.</p>
            <p>The third <hi>Conſideration</hi> is this, The
<hi>ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of the <hi>Lawes;</hi> And this
<hi>Arbitrary power,</hi> as it is <hi>dangerous</hi> to the <hi>Kings
Perſon</hi> and to his <hi>Crowne,</hi> ſo is it in other reſpects very
<hi>prejudiciall</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48451:6"/> to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> in his <hi>Honour,
Profit,</hi> and <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> and yet theſe are the
<hi>gildings</hi> and <hi>paintings</hi> that are put upon ſuch
<hi>counſels;</hi> Theſe are for your <hi>Honour,</hi> for your
<hi>ſervice;</hi> whereas in truth they are contrary to both: But if I
ſhall take off this <hi>varniſh,</hi> I hope they ſhall then appeare in
their owne <hi>native deformity,</hi> and therefore I deſire to conſider
them by theſe <hi>Rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot be for the <hi>Honour</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> that his
<hi>ſacred Authority</hi> ſhould be uſed in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of
<hi>injuſtice</hi> and <hi>oppreſsion;</hi> that his <hi>Name</hi> ſhould
be applyed to <hi>patronize</hi> ſuch <hi>horrid crimes,</hi> as have beene
repreſented in <hi>Evidence</hi> againſt the <hi>Earle of Strafford;</hi>
and yet how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, how preſumptuouſly his <hi>Commands,</hi> his
<hi>Letters</hi> have been vouched throughout the courſe of this
<hi>Defence,</hi> your Lordſhips have heard. When the <hi>Iudges</hi> doe
<hi>juſtice,</hi> it is the <hi>Kings juſtice,</hi> and this is for his
<hi>honour,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the <hi>Fountaine</hi> of <hi>juſtice;</hi>
but when they doe <hi>injuſtice,</hi> the offence is their owne: But thoſe
<hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the King, who are moſt
officious in the exerciſe of this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48451:6"/> 
               <hi>Arbitrarie power,</hi> they doe it commonly
for their advantage; and when they are queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for it, then they fly to
the <hi>Kings intereſt,</hi> to his <hi>Direction:</hi> And truly my Lords,
this is a very unequall <hi>diſtribution</hi> for the King, that the
<hi>diſhonour</hi> of evill <hi>courſes</hi> ſhould be caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him,
and they to have the advantage.</p>
            <p>The <hi>prejudice</hi> which it brings to him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his
<hi>profit,</hi> is no leſſe apparent: It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives him of the moſt
beneficiall, and moſt certaine <hi>Revenue</hi> of his <hi>Crowne,</hi> that
is, the <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary aids</hi> and <hi>ſupplies</hi> of his
<hi>people;</hi> his other <hi>Revenues,</hi> conſiſting of goodly
<hi>Demeanes,</hi> and great <hi>Manors,</hi> have by <hi>Grants</hi> been
alienated from the <hi>Crowne,</hi> and are now exceedingly
<hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed</hi> and <hi>impaired:</hi> But this <hi>Revenue</hi> it
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>ſold,</hi> it cannot be <hi>burdned</hi> with any
<hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> or <hi>Annuities,</hi> but comes intirely to the
<hi>Crowne.</hi> It is now almoſt fifteene years ſince his Majeſty had
any aſſiſtance from his <hi>people;</hi> and theſe illegall wayes of
ſupplying the King were never preſt with more <hi>violence,</hi> and
<hi>art,</hi> then they have been in this time; and yet I may upon very good
<hi>grounds</hi> affirm, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48451:7"/> in the laſt fifteene years of Queen
<hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſhe received more by the <hi>Bounty</hi> and
<hi>Affection</hi> of her <hi>Subjects,</hi> then hath come to His
<hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Coffers</hi> by all the <hi>inordinate</hi> and <hi>rigorous
courſes</hi> which have beene taken. And as thoſe <hi>Supplies</hi> were
more beneficiall in the <hi>Receipt</hi> of them, ſo were they like in the
<hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>Another way of <hi>prejudice</hi> to his <hi>Majeſties
profit,</hi> is this: Such <hi>Arbitrary courſes</hi> exhauſt the people,
and diſable them, when there ſhall be occaſion, to give ſuch plentifull
<hi>ſupplies,</hi> as otherwiſe they would doe. I ſhall need no other
proofe of this, then the <hi>Iriſh Government</hi> under my <hi>L.</hi> of
<hi>Strafford,</hi> where the <hi>wealth</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> is ſo
<hi>conſumed</hi> by thoſe horrible <hi>exactions</hi> and
<hi>burdens,</hi> that it is thought the <hi>Subſidies</hi> lately granted
will amount to little more then halfe the <hi>proportion</hi> of the laſt
<hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies.</hi> The two former wayes are hurtfull to the <hi>Kings
profit,</hi> in that reſpect which they call <hi>Lucrum Ceſſans,</hi> by
diminiſhing his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts; But there is a third, fuller of
<hi>miſchiefe,</hi> and it is in that reſpect which they call
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48451:7"/> 
               <hi>Damnum emergens,</hi> by increaſing his
<hi>Disburſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> Such <hi>irregular</hi> and <hi>exorbitant
attempts</hi> upon the <hi>Libertie</hi> of the <hi>people,</hi> are apt to
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce ſuch miſerable <hi>diſtractions</hi> and <hi>diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi>
as will put the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> to ſuch vaſt
<hi>expences</hi> and <hi>loſſes</hi> in a ſhort time, as will not be
recovered in many yeares: Wee need not goe farre to ſeeke a proofe of this,
theſe two laſt yeares will be a ſufficient evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, within which time I
aſſure my ſelfe, it may be proved, that more <hi>Treaſure</hi> hath
beene waſted, more loſſe ſuſtained by his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his
<hi>Subjects,</hi> then was ſpent by Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in all the War
of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> and in thoſe many brave <hi>Attempts</hi> againſt the
King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the royall <hi>aſsiſtance</hi> which ſhe
gave to <hi>France,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all her
<hi>Reigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>Greatneſſe,</hi> this <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> is
apt to hinder and impaire it, not onely at home, but abroad. A
<hi>Kingdome</hi> is a <hi>ſociety</hi> of men conjoyned under one
Government, for the <hi>common good:</hi> The <hi>world</hi> is a ſociety of
<hi>Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>States.</hi> The <hi>Kings greatneſſe</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48451:8"/> conſiſts not onely in his <hi>Dominion</hi>
over his <hi>Subjects</hi> at home, but in the <hi>influence</hi> which he hath
upon <hi>States</hi> abroad; That he ſhould be great even among
<hi>Kings,</hi> and by his <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>authority</hi> ſo to
incline and diſpoſe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of other <hi>States</hi> and
<hi>Nations,</hi> and thoſe great <hi>events</hi> which fall out in the
<hi>world,</hi> as ſhall be for the good of <hi>Mankind,</hi> and for the
peculiar <hi>advantage</hi> of his owne people. This is the moſt
<hi>glorious,</hi> and <hi>magnificent greatneſs,</hi> to be able to relieve
<hi>diſtreſsed Princes,</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his owne <hi>friends</hi> and
<hi>Allies,</hi> to prevent the <hi>ambitious deſignes</hi> of other
<hi>Kings;</hi> and how much this Kingdome hath been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired in this kinde,
by the late <hi>miſchievous counſels</hi> your Lordſhips beſt know, who
at a neerer diſtance, and with a more cleare ſight, doe apprehend theſe
publique and great affaires, then I can doe. Yet thus much I dare boldly ſay,
that if his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> had not with great <hi>wiſdome</hi> and
<hi>goodneſs</hi> forſaken that way wherein the <hi>Earle</hi> of
<hi>Strafford</hi> had put him, we ſhould within a ſhort time have been
brought into that <hi>miſerable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as to have been
uſeleſſe to our <hi>friends,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48451:8"/> to our <hi>enemies,</hi> and uncapable of
undertaking any great <hi>deſigne</hi> either at home or abroad.</p>
            <p>A fourth Conſideration is, That this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and Tyrannicall Power, which the <hi>E.</hi> of
<hi>Strafford</hi> did exerciſe in his own perſon, and to which he did
adviſe his Majeſty, is inconſiſtent with the Peace, the Wealth, the
Proſperity of a Nation; It is deſtructive to Juſtice, the Mother of
Peace; to Induſtry, the ſpring of Wealth; to Valour, which is the active
vertue whereby the proſperity of a Nation can onely be procured, confirmed,
and inlarged.</p>
            <p>It is not only apt to take away Peace, and ſo intangle the
Nation with Warres, but doth corrupt Peace, and puts ſuch a malignity into
it, as produceth the Effects of warre. We need ſeek no other proofe of this,
but the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Straffords</hi> Government, where the
<hi>Iriſh,</hi> both <hi>Nobility</hi> and others, had as little
<hi>ſecurity</hi> of their <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Eſtates</hi> in this
peaceable <hi>time,</hi> as if the <hi>Kingdome</hi> had been under the
<hi>rage</hi> and <hi>fury</hi> of <hi>warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48451:9"/> And as for <hi>Induſtrie,</hi> and
<hi>Valour,</hi> who will take pains for that, which when he hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, is
not his own? Or who fight for that wherein he hath no other
<hi>intereſt,</hi> but ſuch as is ſubject to the will of another? The
<hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent encouragement</hi> to men that were to defend their
<hi>Countries</hi> was this, That they were to hazard their <hi>Perſons, pro
Aris &amp; Focis,</hi> for their <hi>Religion,</hi> and for their
<hi>Houſes;</hi> But by this <hi>Arbitrary</hi> way which was practiſed in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> and counſelled here, no man had any <hi>certainty,</hi>
either of <hi>Religion,</hi> or of his <hi>Houſe,</hi> or any thing elſe to
be his own; But beſides this, ſuch <hi>Arbitrary</hi> courſes have an ill
ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration upon the <hi>courage</hi> of a Nation, by em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing the
<hi>hearts</hi> of the <hi>people: A ſervile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition doth for the moſt
part beget in men a ſlaviſh temper and diſpoſition. Thoſe</hi> that
live ſo much under the <hi>Whip</hi> and the <hi>Pillory,</hi> and ſuch
<hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile Engines,</hi> as were frequently <hi>uſed</hi> by the
<hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Strafford,</hi> they may have the <hi>dregges</hi> of
<hi>valour, ſullenneſſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtubbornneſſe,</hi> which
may make them <hi>prone</hi> to <hi>Mutinies,</hi> and <hi>diſcontents;</hi>
but thoſe <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>gallant affections,</hi> which put men on
<hi>brave Deſignes</hi> and <hi>Attempts</hi> for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48451:9"/> the <hi>preſervation</hi> or
<hi>inlargement</hi> of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> they are hardly <hi>capable</hi>
of. Shall it be <hi>Treaſon</hi> to <hi>embaſe</hi> the <hi>Kings
Coyne,</hi> though but a <hi>piece</hi> of <hi>twelve-pence,</hi> or
<hi>ſixe-pence,</hi> and muſt it not needs be the <hi>effect</hi> of a
greater <hi>Treaſon,</hi> to <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe</hi> the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of his
<hi>Subjects,</hi> and to ſet a <hi>ſtamp</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of
<hi>ſervitude</hi> upon them, whereby they ſhall be <hi>diſabled</hi> to
doe any thing for the ſervice of the <hi>King</hi> or
<hi>Common-wealth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fift <hi>Conſideration</hi> is this, That the
<hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> of this <hi>Arbitrary Government,</hi>
in times of <hi>ſudden danger,</hi> by the <hi>invaſion</hi> of an
<hi>enemy,</hi> will <hi>diſable</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to
<hi>preſerve himſelfe</hi> and <hi>his Subjects</hi> from that
<hi>danger.</hi> This is the onely <hi>pretence</hi> by which the <hi>E.</hi>
of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and ſuch other <hi>miſchievous Counſellors</hi>
would <hi>induce</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> to make <hi>uſe</hi> of it; and
if it be <hi>unfit</hi> for ſuch an <hi>occaſion,</hi> I know nothing that
can be <hi>alledged</hi> in <hi>maintenance</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>When <hi>warre threatens</hi> a <hi>Kingdome</hi> by the
<hi>comming</hi> of a <hi>forrain Enemy,</hi> it is <hi>no time</hi> then to
<hi>diſcontent</hi> the <hi>people,</hi> to make them <hi>weary</hi> of the
<hi>preſent Government,</hi> and more <hi>inclinable</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:48451:10"/> to a <hi>Change;</hi> The <hi>ſupplies</hi>
which are to come in this <hi>way,</hi> will be <hi>unready, uncertain;</hi>
there can be no <hi>aſſurance</hi> of them, no <hi>dependence</hi> upon
them, either for <hi>time</hi> or <hi>proportion:</hi> And if ſome money be
gotten in ſuch a way, the <hi>Diſtractions, Diviſions, Diſtempers,</hi>
which this <hi>courſe</hi> is apt to <hi>produce,</hi> will be more
<hi>prejudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> to the <hi>publique ſafety,</hi> then the
<hi>ſupply</hi> can be <hi>advantagious</hi> to it; and of this we have had
<hi>ſufficient experience</hi> the <hi>laſt Summer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſixt, That this <hi>crime</hi> of <hi>ſubverting</hi> the
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>introducing</hi> an
<hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall Government,</hi> is <hi>contrary</hi>
to the <hi>Pact</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi> betwixt the <hi>King</hi> and his
<hi>people.</hi> That which was ſpoken of before, was the <hi>legall
union</hi> of <hi>Allegeance</hi> and <hi>Protection;</hi> this is a
<hi>perſonall union</hi> by <hi>mutuall agreement</hi> and
<hi>ſtipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, confirmed</hi> by <hi>oath</hi> on both <hi>ſides:</hi>
The <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>people</hi> are <hi>obliged</hi> to one another
in the <hi>neareſt relations;</hi> He is a <hi>Father,</hi> and a
<hi>childe</hi> is called in <hi>Law, Pars Patris:</hi> Hee is the
<hi>Husband</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> they have the <hi>ſame
intereſts,</hi> they are <hi>inſeparable</hi> in their <hi>condition,</hi>
be it <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evill;</hi> He is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48451:10"/> 
               <hi>Head,</hi> they are the <hi>Body;</hi>
there is ſuch an <hi>incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration</hi> as cannot be diſſolved without
the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of both.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Iuſtice Thorpe,</hi> in <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>thirds
time,</hi> was by the <hi>Parliament condemned</hi> to <hi>death</hi> for
<hi>Bribery,</hi> the <hi>reaſon</hi> of that Judgement is given, becauſe
he had <hi>broken</hi> the <hi>Kings Oath,</hi> not that he had broken his own
<hi>oath,</hi> but that he had broken the <hi>Kings oath,</hi> that
<hi>ſolemne</hi> and <hi>great obligation,</hi> which is the
<hi>ſecurity</hi> of the <hi>whole Kingdome:</hi> If for a Judge to take a
ſmall <hi>ſumme</hi> in a private cauſe, was adjudged <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</hi>
how much greater was this <hi>offence,</hi> whereby the <hi>E.</hi> of
<hi>Strafford</hi> hath broken the <hi>Kings Oath</hi> in the whole
<hi>courſe</hi> of his <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the
<hi>prejudice</hi> of ſo many of his <hi>Majeſties Subjects,</hi> in their
<hi>Lives, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and to the danger of all the
reſt?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts, Fides non eſt
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanda cum Haereticis,</hi> is an <hi>abominable Doctrine:</hi> yet that
other Tenet more <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> is more
<hi>pernicious,</hi> whereby <hi>Subjects</hi> are <hi>diſcharged</hi> from
their <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegeance</hi> to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48451:11"/> their <hi>Prince</hi> whenſoever the
<hi>Pope</hi> pleaſeth; This may be added to make the <hi>third</hi> no
leſſe <hi>miſchievous</hi> and <hi>deſtructive</hi> to <hi>humane
ſociety,</hi> then either of the reſt; That the King is not bound by that
<hi>Oath</hi> which he hath taken to <hi>obſerve</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of
the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> but may when he ſees <hi>cauſe,</hi> lay
<hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>burdens</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them without their
<hi>conſent,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the
<hi>Kingdome.</hi> This hath been <hi>preached</hi> and <hi>publiſhed</hi> by
divers; And this is that which hath been <hi>practiſed</hi> in
<hi>Ireland</hi> by the <hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Strafford,</hi> in his
<hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there,</hi> and indeavoured to be brought into
<hi>England,</hi> by his <hi>Counſell here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeventh is this; It is an <hi>offence</hi> that is
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> contrary to the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> The
<hi>end</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> was to prevent <hi>oppreſsions,</hi> to
limit and reſtrain the exceſſive power and violence of <hi>great
men,</hi> to <hi>open</hi> the paſſages of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> with
<hi>indifferency</hi> towards all; This <hi>Arbitrary</hi> power is apt to
<hi>induce</hi> and incourage all kind of <hi>inſolencies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> is to
<hi>preſerve</hi> men in their <hi>eſtates,</hi> to <hi>ſecure</hi> them
in their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48451:11"/> Lives and Liberties; but if this Deſigne had
taken effect, and could have been <hi>ſetled</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> as it
was <hi>practiſed</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> no man would have had more
certainty in his own, then power would have allowed him: But theſe two have
been ſpoken of before, there are two behind more <hi>important,</hi> which
have not yet been touched.</p>
            <p>It is the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> that
<hi>vertue</hi> ſhould be <hi>cheriſht, vice ſuppreſt;</hi> but where
this <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>unlimited power</hi> is ſet up, a way is open
not onely for the <hi>ſecurity,</hi> but for the <hi>advancement</hi> and
<hi>incouragement</hi> of evill; Such men as are apteſt for the execution and
maintenance of this Power, are onely capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of preferment; and others who
will not be <hi>inſtruments</hi> of any <hi>unjuſt commands,</hi> who make
a <hi>conſcience</hi> to doe nothing againſt the <hi>Laws</hi> of the
<hi>Kingdome,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi> are not
onely not <hi>paſſable</hi> for <hi>imployment,</hi> but <hi>ſubject</hi>
to much <hi>jealouſie</hi> and <hi>danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> that all
<hi>accidents</hi> and <hi>events,</hi> all <hi>Counſels</hi> and
<hi>Deſignes</hi> ſhould be improved to the <hi>publique good:</hi> But
this <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48451:12"/> 
               <hi>Power</hi> is apt to <hi>diſpoſe</hi>
all to the <hi>mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of it ſelf. The <hi>wiſdome</hi> of the
<hi>Councell-Table,</hi> the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Courts</hi> of
Juſtice, the <hi>induſtry</hi> of all the <hi>Officers</hi> of the
<hi>Crown</hi> have been moſt carefully <hi>exerciſed</hi> in this; the
<hi>Learning</hi> of our <hi>Divines,</hi> the <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> of our
<hi>Biſhops</hi> have been moulded and diſpoſed to the ſame
<hi>effect,</hi> which though it were begun before the <hi>E.</hi> of
<hi>Straffords Imployment,</hi> yet it hath beene exceedingly
<hi>furthered</hi> and <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced</hi> by him.</p>
            <p>Under this <hi>colour</hi> and <hi>pretence</hi> of
<hi>maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> the <hi>Kings Power</hi> and <hi>Prerogative</hi> many
<hi>dangerous practiſes</hi> againſt the <hi>peace</hi> and
<hi>ſafety</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> have been undertaken and promoted.
The <hi>increaſe</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> and the favours and incouragement
of <hi>Papiſts</hi> have been, and ſtill are a great grievance and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
to the <hi>Kingdome:</hi> The <hi>Innovations</hi> in <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of
<hi>Religion,</hi> the <hi>uſurpations</hi> of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> the
manifold burdens and taxations upon the people, have been a great cauſe of
our preſent <hi>diſtempers</hi> and <hi>diſorders;</hi> and yet thoſe
who have been chiefe <hi>Furtherers</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48451:12"/> ſuch Miſchiefes, have had their Credit and
Authority from this, That they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>maintain</hi> this Power.
The E. of <hi>Strafford</hi> had the firſt riſe of his greatneſſe from
this, and in his <hi>Apologie</hi> and <hi>Defence,</hi> as your
<hi>Lordſhips</hi> have heard, this hath had a maine part.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Royall Power,</hi> and <hi>Majeſty</hi> of
<hi>Kings,</hi> is moſt glorious in the <hi>proſperity</hi> and
<hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the people; The perfection of all things
conſiſts in the <hi>end</hi> for which they were ordained, <hi>God</hi>
onely is his own <hi>end,</hi> all other <hi>things</hi> have a further
<hi>end</hi> beyond <hi>themſelves,</hi> in attaining whereof their own
happineſſe conſiſts: If the <hi>means</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> be
ſet in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to one another, it muſt needs <hi>cauſe</hi>
an <hi>impotency</hi> and <hi>defect</hi> of <hi>both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The eight <hi>Conſideration</hi> is, The <hi>vanity</hi> and
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>abſurdity</hi> of thoſe <hi>excuſes</hi> and
<hi>juſtifications</hi> which he made for himſelf, whereof divers
<hi>particulars</hi> have been mentioned in the <hi>courſe</hi> of his
<hi>Defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:48451:13"/> 1. That he is a <hi>Counſellor,</hi> and
might not be <hi>queſtioned</hi> for any thing which he adviſed according
to his <hi>conſcience;</hi> The <hi>ground</hi> is <hi>true,</hi> there is a
<hi>liberty</hi> belongs to <hi>Counſellors,</hi> and nothing corrupts
Counſels more then <hi>fear; He</hi> that will have the priviledge of a
<hi>Counſellor,</hi> muſt keep within the iuſt bounds of a
<hi>Counſellor;</hi> thoſe <hi>matters</hi> are the proper
<hi>ſubjects</hi> of <hi>Counſell,</hi> which in their times and
occaſions, may be good or beneficiall to the <hi>King</hi> or
<hi>Common-wealth;</hi> But ſuch <hi>Treaſons</hi> as theſe, the
<hi>ſubverſion</hi> of the <hi>Laws, violation</hi> of <hi>Liberties,</hi>
they can never be good, or juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by any <hi>circumſtance,</hi> or
<hi>occaſion;</hi> and therefore his being a <hi>Counſellor,</hi> makes his
fault much more hainous, as being commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt a greater
<hi>Truſt,</hi> and in a way of much miſchiefe and danger, leſt his
Majeſties conſcience and judgement (upon which the whole courſe and frame
of his <hi>Government</hi> do much depend) ſhould be poyſoned and infected
with ſuch wicked principles and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes: And this he hath endeavoured to
doe, which by all <hi>Lawes,</hi> and in all <hi>times</hi> hath in this
<hi>Kingdome</hi> beene reckoned
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48451:13"/> a <hi>Crime</hi> of an <hi>high
Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He labours to <hi>intereſt</hi> your Lordſhips in his
<hi>cauſe,</hi> by alledging, It may be <hi>dangerous</hi> to your ſelves,
and your <hi>Poſterity,</hi> who by your <hi>birth</hi> are fitteſt to be
near his Majeſty, in places of <hi>Truſt</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> if
you ſhould be ſubject to be <hi>queſtioned</hi> for <hi>matters</hi>
delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in <hi>Counſell.</hi> To this was anſwered, that it was
<hi>hoped</hi> their Lordſhips would rather <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> to ſecure
themſelves, and their poſterity, in the exerciſe of their
<hi>vertues,</hi> then of their <hi>vices,</hi> that ſo they might together
with their own <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> preſerve the
<hi>honour</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> both of the <hi>King</hi> and
<hi>Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Another <hi>excuſe</hi> was this, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he
hath <hi>ſpoken</hi> was out of a <hi>good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Sometimes
<hi>good</hi> and <hi>evill, truth</hi> and <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood</hi> lie ſo near
together, that they are hardly to be <hi>diſtinguiſhed:</hi> Matters
<hi>hurtfull</hi> and <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous</hi> may be accompanied with ſuch
<hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> as may make it appeare uſefull and convenient, and
in all ſuch <hi>caſes, good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> will juſtifie <hi>evill
Counſell;</hi> But where the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48451:14"/> matters propounded are <hi>evill</hi> in their
own <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>matters</hi> are wherewith the
<hi>E.</hi> of <hi>Strafford</hi> is charged, to <hi>break</hi> a <hi>publique
faith,</hi> to <hi>ſubvert Laws</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> they can never
be juſtified by any intentions, how ſpecious, or good ſoever they be
pretended.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He <hi>alledgeth</hi> it was a time of great
<hi>neceſsity</hi> and <hi>danger,</hi> when ſuch counſels were
<hi>neceſſary</hi> for preſervation of the <hi>State. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity</hi>
hath been ſpoken of before, as it relates to the Cauſe; now it is
conſidered as it relates to the Perſon; if there were any neceſſity, it
was of his own making; he by his <hi>evil</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell had brought the
<hi>King</hi> into a neceſſity, and by no Rules of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> can
be <hi>allowed</hi> to gain this advantage by his own fault, as to make that a
<hi>ground</hi> of his juſtification, which is a great part of his
offence.</p>
            <p n="5">5. He hath often <hi>inſinuated</hi> this, That it was for
his Majeſties ſervice in <hi>maintenance</hi> of that Soveraign
<hi>Power</hi> with which he is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted</hi> by <hi>God</hi> for the
<hi>good</hi> of his people. The Anſwer is this, No doubt but that Soveraign
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48451:14"/> Power wherewith his Majeſty is
<hi>intruſted</hi> for the publique good, hath many glorious
<hi>effects,</hi> the better to inable him thereunto; But without doubt this is
none of them, That by his own will he may lay any <hi>Taxe</hi> or
<hi>Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> upon his people without their conſent in
<hi>Parliament.</hi> This hath now been five times adjudged by both
<hi>Houſes:</hi> In the Caſe of the <hi>Loanes,</hi> In condemning the
<hi>Commiſsion</hi> of <hi>Exciſe,</hi> In the Reſolution upon the
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> offered to be added to the <hi>Petition</hi> of
<hi>Right,</hi> In the ſentence againſt <hi>Manwaring,</hi> and now lately,
In condemning the <hi>Ship-money;</hi> And if the Soveraigne Power of the King
can produce no ſuch <hi>effect</hi> as this, the <hi>Allegation</hi> of it is
an Aggravation, and no Diminution of his offence, becauſe thereby he doth
labour to intereſt the King againſt the juſt grievance and complaint of
the People.</p>
            <p n="6">6. This <hi>Counſell</hi> was propounded with divers
<hi>limitations,</hi> and <hi>Proviſions;</hi> for ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and repairing
the <hi>liberty</hi> of the <hi>people.</hi> This implies a
<hi>contradiction</hi> to maintain an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> &amp; abſolute
Power, and yet to reſtrain it with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48451:15"/> 
               <hi>limitations,</hi> and
<hi>proviſions;</hi> for even thoſe <hi>limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> and
<hi>proviſions</hi> will be ſubject to the ſame abſolute
<hi>Power,</hi> and to be diſpenſed in ſuch manner, and at ſuch time,
as it ſelf ſhall determine; let the <hi>grievances</hi> and
<hi>oppreſsions</hi> be never ſo heavy, the <hi>Subject</hi> is left
without all remedy, but at his Majeſties own pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="7">7. He alledgeth, they were but <hi>words,</hi> and no
<hi>effect</hi> followed: This needs no anſwer, but that the <hi>miſerable
diſtempers</hi> into which he hath brought all the three Kingdomes, will be
evidence ſufficient that his wicked <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> have had ſuch
<hi>miſchievous</hi> effects within theſe two or three laſt years, that
many years peace will hardly repaire thoſe loſſes, and other great
miſchiefes which the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> hath ſuſtained.</p>
            <p>Theſe excuſes have been collected out of the ſeverall parts
of his <hi>Defence;</hi> perchance ſome others are omitted, which I doubt not
have been anſwered by ſome of my Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legues, and are of no importance,
either to perplex or to hinder your Lordſhips judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48451:15"/> touching the hainouſneſſe of this
Crime.</p>
            <p>The ninth <hi>Conſideration</hi> is this, That if
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> this be <hi>Treaſon,</hi> in the nature of it, it doth
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed all other <hi>Treaſons</hi> in this, That in the Deſign, and
endeavour of the Author, it was to be a <hi>conſtant</hi> and a <hi>permanent
Treaſon;</hi> other Treaſons are tranſient, as being confinde within
thoſe particular <hi>actions</hi> and <hi>proportions</hi> wherein they did
conſiſt, and thoſe being paſt, the <hi>Treaſon</hi> ceaſeth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Powder-Treaſon</hi> was full of horror and malignity,
yet it is paſt many years ſince; The <hi>murder</hi> of that
<hi>Magnanimous</hi> and <hi>glorious King, Henry the fourth</hi> of
<hi>France,</hi> was a great and horrid <hi>Treaſon;</hi> And ſo were
thoſe manifold attempts againſt Qu. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of bleſſed
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; but they are long ſince paſt, the <hi>Dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation</hi> of them
only remains in <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> and in the <hi>minds</hi> of men; and
will ever remain; But this <hi>Treaſon,</hi> if it had taken effect, was to
be a ſtanding, perpetuall <hi>Treaſon,</hi> which would have been in
<hi>continuall act,</hi> not <hi>determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> within one <hi>time</hi> or
<hi>age,</hi> but <hi>tranſmitted</hi> to <hi>Poſterity,</hi> even from
<hi>generation</hi> to <hi>generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48451:16"/> The tenth <hi>Conſideration</hi> is this,
That as it is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> a Crime odious in the nature of it, ſo it
is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the judgement and eſtimation of the <hi>Law;</hi> To alter the
ſetled <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> is
<hi>Treaſon</hi> in any <hi>eſtate;</hi> The <hi>Laws</hi> whereby all
other parts of a Kingdome are preſerved, ſhould be very vain and
defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, if they had not a <hi>power</hi> to ſecure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<hi>themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>forfeitures</hi> inflicted for <hi>Treaſon</hi> by our
Law, are of <hi>Life, Honour,</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> even all that can be
<hi>forfeited,</hi> and this Priſoner having committed ſo many Treaſons,
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he ſhould pay all theſe <hi>forfeitures,</hi> will be ſtill a
Debtor to the <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> Nothing can be more equall then that he
ſhould periſh by the Juſtice of that Law which he would have ſubverted;
Neither wil this be a new way of bloud; There are marks enough to trace this
Law to the very origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of this Kingdome: And if it hath not been put in
execution, as he alledgeth, this 240. years, it was not for want of Law, but
that all that time hath not bred a man bold enough to commit ſuch Crimes as
theſe;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48451:16"/> which is a <hi>circumſtance</hi> much
aggravating his offence, and making him no whit leſſe liable to
puniſhment, becauſe he is the onely man that in ſo long a time hath
ventured upon ſuch a <hi>Treaſon</hi> as this.</p>
            <p>It belongs to the charge of another to make it appear to your
Lordſhips, that the Crimes and Offences proved againſt the <hi>Earle</hi>
of <hi>Strafford,</hi> are <hi>High Treaſon</hi> by the Lawes and Statutes of
this Realm, whoſe learning and other abilities are much better for that
ſervice. But for the time and manner of performing this, we are to reſort
to the <hi>Direction</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> having in this
which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done, diſpatched all thoſe inſtructions which wee have
received; and concerning further proceedings, for clearing all Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and
Objections in Law, your Lordſhips will hear from the <hi>Houſe</hi> of
<hi>Commons</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
